<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Django From the Ground Up | Eric Florenzano's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://ericflo.github.com/blog/categories/django-from-the-ground-up/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ericflo.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-01-01T15:38:17-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://ericflo.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Eric Florenzano]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA["Django From the Ground Up" Screencast Series Launched]]></title>
    <link href="http://ericflo.github.com/blog/2008/09/18/django-ground-screencast-series-launched/"/>
    <updated>2008-09-18T21:33:09-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://ericflo.github.com/blog/2008/09/18/django-ground-screencast-series-launched</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
Over the past few weeks I've been busy coding, planning, and recording a series of screencasts which walk through the complete process of building a web application, from the ground up, with Django.  First I actually needed to code the site, deploy the site, and release the source code for the site.  Then, I had to go back and decide what in that whole process was worth talking about.  Finally, I had to re-code the site, but this time in front of the camera.  It's been a long process so far and I'm not finished yet, but tonight is the night that I am finally able to unveil the first two episodes.</p>

<p>If you haven't checked them out yet, head over to <code>their spot on thisweekindjango.com</code>_.</p>

<p>One thing that I'm a little bit worried about is that, by the very nature of going every step along the way, there are going to be some times where a topic I cover is on the more advanced side of things, and there are going to be topics that I cover which are on the more beginner side of things.  That can be fine, but there's a risk that in targeting such a broad audience, nobody ends up enjoying it.  As long as at least one person gets something out of the screencasts, I'll be happy.</p>

<p>So please, I only have 7 screencasts recorded so far, which means there is still time to turn this boat around!  If you have any suggestions or comments or questions, please leave a comment either here or on the <code>episode's page at thisweekindjango.com</code>_.</p>

<p>.. <em><code>their spot on thisweekindjango.com</code>: http://thisweekindjango.com/screencasts/episode/10/django-ground-episodes-1-and-2/
.. </em><code>episode's page at thisweekindjango.com</code>: http://thisweekindjango.com/screencasts/episode/10/django-ground-episodes-1-and-2/
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
